Finding Aid for Francis Wayland Dunn papers, 1856-1874
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Francis Wayland Dunn papers 1856-1874
Dunn, Francis Wayland, 1843-1874.
2 linear feet (20 volumes and 36 folders)
861150 Aa 2
Student at Hillsdale College, soldier during the Civil War with the 64th Illinois Volunteers. Diaries, 1860-1872, describing student life, wartime activities, trip to Europe and the Near East, and western trip containing impressions of Indians and Mormons; also correspondence, various writings, and commonplace book, 1872.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the Dunn-Slayton family (donor no. 3361 ) and came to the library in 1957.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Francis Wayland Dunn was born January 29, 1843 in Wayne, Astabula County, Ohio. Following graduation from Hillsdale College in 1862 Dunn enlisted in Company A, 64th Illinois Infantry. He later served in Company H, First Alabama Cavalry (Union) as sergeant major. After the war, Dunn taught at Hillsdale College. He also traveled extensively in the Middle East and much of Europe. He died December 13, 1873.
The Francis Wayland Dunn collection consists of diaries, correspondence, writings, and miscellaneous personal materials.
Subjects:
Dunn, Ransom, 1818-1900.; Europe--Description and travel.; Hillsdale College.; Middle East--Description and travel.; Voyages and travels.; United States. Army. Illinois Infantry Regiment, 64th (1861-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; West (U.S.)--Description and travel.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Diaries
  The diaries cover the period of 1860-1872. From September 1862 to November 1864, Wayland, and his brother Ransom, were mustered into the Yates Sharpshooters, 64th Regiment Illinois Volunteers. In the summer of 1863 Wayland became sergeant major of 'H' Co., Alabama Volunteers, First U.S. Cavalry (Union). The diaries provide detailed daily entries spanning his entire period of service. Wayland participated in campaigns in the following states -Arkansas, Tennessee, Mississippi, Alabama, and Georgia. Details are given of camp life, various skirmishes, the effect of the war on the south, foraging parties, the burning of Corinth, battlefield scenes and the siege at Lookout Mountain.
  A diary entry in May 1865 describes a visit to Chicago, where Dunn paid his respects to the martyred President Lincoln whose body was lying in state in the City Hall building. Later that same year, Wayland and a friend went on a sightseeing trip. Leaving New York on November 25, the tour included England, France, Italy, Egypt, Palestine, Turkey (Ottoman Empire), a Danube excursion, Austria, Prussia, Netherlands, Scotland and Canada - in that order. During the entire tour, extensive daily entries (2 - 5 pp.) provide details of places visited, and Wayland's impressions of the people and living conditions. There are approximately 750 pages of entries describing the trip. During July-August 1868, Wayland relates his experiences while traveling by horseback in Kansas and Nebraska. The diary entries describe taking part in buffalo hunts, Indian life, customs, games, etc. He also mentions witnessing a near fight between Sioux and Pawnees. In October-November 1868, Wayland relates his experiences among the Mormons in Utah. He tells of Mormon meetings, life, efforts to rid Salt Lake City of non-Mormon merchants. Wayland attended several meetings where Brigham Young was present. He also talked with a young son of Brigham about the leader's family life. In 1869-1870, he describes a trip through California.
  - 1860 (Box 1)
  - 1860-1862 (Box 1)
  - Diary fragments: Camp Life, 1862 (Box 1)
  - Diary fragments: Civil War, 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Diary fragments (Box 1)
    (including maps, writings of W.J. Dennis and C.C. Nelson, and miscellaneous)
  - August 1864-December 1864 (Box 1)
  - January 1865-November 1865 (Box 1)
  - November 1865-March 1866 (Box 1)
  - March 1866-May 1866 (Box 1)
  - May 1866-July 1866 (Box 1)
  - July 1866-January 1867 (Box 1)
  - January 1867-May 1867 (Box 1)
  - May 1867-February 1868 (Box 1)
  - February 1868-May 1868 (Box 1)
  - June 1868-October 1868 (Box 1)
  - October 1868-July 1869 (Box 1)
  - 1868-1869 (Box 1)
  - July 1869-March 1870 (Box 1)
  - April 1870-December 1870 (Box 1)
  - April 1871-April 1872 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The correspondence dates from 1856 to 1876. As a whole the correspondence is of a personal nature, useful primarily for biographical purposes. There are numerous letters from his father, Reverend Ransom Dunn, while Wayland attended school and college, and during his service in the Civil War. Very little of the correspondence deals with Michigan subjects other than student life at Hillsdale College. Most of the college friends with whom Wayland corresponded were not Michigan residents.
  - By date (Box 2)
    - 1856-1876, 18 folders (Box 2)
  - By name
    - Davis, Julian, 1860-1864 (Box 2)
    - Dunn, Ransom, 1854-1865, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Hopkins, John J., 1862-1864 (Box 2)
    - Pratt, R.H., 1861-1864 (Box 2)
    - Stark, J.H., 1861-1862 (Box 2)
      (include letters from J. H. Stark, volunteer, probably a New Yorker stationed at Camp Union Hill near Baltimore, and later with the Army of the Potomac under McClellan)
- Other materials
  Within the Other Materials series, there are several folders of manuscript writings consisting principally of articles for the Christian Freeman. Wayland was editor of the paper for several brief periods in the late 1860s. One interesting article concerns Mormon life. The remainder deal with religious topics, prohibition and current events.
  - Civil War miscellaneous, including war records, musters, affidavits, discharge papers, etc. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, including correspondence of Southern Soldier, draft of play, verse, etc. (passport) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 8 folders (Box 2)
  - Commonplace book, 1872 (Box 2)
Related Material
The library also has collections of papers of Dunn's father Ransom Dunn and his brother Newell Ransom Dunn.